Guide to the William Adams Delano Collection 1899-1949, undated PR 244
New-York Historical Society
William Adams Delano Collection
1899-1949, undated
New-York Historical Society
PR 244
3.25 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The William Adams Delano Collection contains photographs and drawings documenting his education in Paris, and some photographs of the projects his architecture firm designed.
Provenance
Gift of William Adams Delano, May 29, 1956, and June 28, 1956.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
William Adams Delano (1874-1960) was born in New York, was a graduate of the Lawrenceville School and Yale University, and studied architecture at Columbia University and at the Ecole des Beaux Arts in Paris. After working in the New York firm of Carrere & Hastings, he formed a design firm with Chester Holmes Aldrich (1871-1940) in 1903
Further information on Delano and his firm can be found in Peter Pennoyer and Anne Walker, The Architecture of Delano & Aldrich (New York and London: W. W. Norton & Co., 2003). The book includes a chronology of the architects' life and design projects.
Scope and Content Note
The William Adams Delano Collection spans the period from 1899 through the 1940s; it contains photographs and drawings documenting his education in Paris, and some of the projects his architecture firm designed.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following series:
Series I. Photographs
Series II. Student Drawings
Series III. Commissions
Oversize material from Series I.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Drawings by Delano & Aldrich for the Battery Park (New York City) design competition are in the Architects and Engineers File (PR 003). The Delano & Aldrich firm's archive is at the Avery Art and Architecture Library, Columbia University.
Technical drawings; Photographic prints.; Architectural drawings; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs; College buildings -- United States -- Pictorial works; Architecture -- United States -- Pictorial works; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century; Cornell University; Delano & Aldrich; Duryea, Drix, photographer; Fischer, Sigurd, photographer; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards, d. 1956, photographer; Wurts Bros., photographer; Yale University
- Series I: Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I holds vintage original photographs of buildings designed by the firm of Delano & Aldrich. They are arranged in two subseries: Commissions, and Competition Drawings, filed alphabetically by the name of the client. Commissions includes homes and estates, academic buildings at Cornell and Yale universities, private clubs, and government buildings, primarily in the United States. Competition drawings are photographs of presentation drawings made for potential commissions. No attempt was made to assign dates to either the photographs or the projects. Photographers included are Mattie Edwards Hewitt, Drix Duryea, Sigurd Fischer, and Wurts Brothers.
  - Subseries I: Commissions
    Photographs are arranged alphabetically by client.
    - Astor, Vincent, Sands Point, NY (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baker, George F., Jr., New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brook Club, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Burden, James A., estate (Woodside), Syosset, NY (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapin School, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cornell University, Willard Straight Hall, Ithaca, NY (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Debevoise, Thomas, Green Village, N (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Delano & Aldrich, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dutch Reformed Church, Brookville, NY (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - John F. Kennedy Airport, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Kahn, Otto H., estate (Oheka), Cold Spring Harbor, NY (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
      General note
      See: Oversize photographs, Box 2
    - Kips Bay Boys Club, New York, N (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - La Guardia Airport, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Morawetz, Victor, estate (Three Ponds), Woodbury, NY (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Staten Island Savings Bank, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Straight, Willard D., New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Straight, Willard D., Westbury, NY (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1040 Park Avenue, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Tree, Ronald F., estate (Mirador), Greenwood, VA (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Tuck, William H., estate, Waterloo, Belgium (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Union Club, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - United States Government Building, Paris, France--Interiors and floor plans (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - United States Government Building, Paris, France--Exteriors (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - United States Post Office Department, Washington, DC (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Walters Art Gallery, Baltimore, MD (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Whitney, Gertrude Vanderbilt, Westbury, NY (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Wood, Chalmers, estate (Little Ipswich), Syosset, NY (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Yale University, Sage Hall, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Yale University, Sterling Chemistry Laboratory, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Yale University, Sterling Divinity School, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Yale University, William L. Harkness Hall, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Yale University, Wright Memorial Hall, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Subseries I: Competitions
    Photographs are arranged alphabetically by competition.
    - Chateau des Beaux-Arts, Huntington, NY (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Federal Reserve Bank, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Federal Reserve Board [Washington, DC?] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Museum of the City of New York, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - New Haven City Hall, New Haven, CT (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - New York City Court Courthouse, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Theodore Roosevelt Memorial, Washington, DC (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - United States Department of Justice [Washington, DC?] (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Waterbury City Hall, Waterbury, CT (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Unidentified airport [?] retail plaza and parking lot [?] (Box 1, Folder unknown container)
    - Frick Residence (East 71st Street elevation, courtyard and garden), New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Scope and Contents
      small pencil drawings
    - Unidentified theatre (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Series II: Student Drawings
  Series II contains twenty-one drawings, dating from 1899 to 1901, made by Delano during his years as a student at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts in Paris. While in Paris, Delano was part of the atelier of Victor-Alexandre-Frederic Laloux (1850-1937), a noted architect and one of the academy's great instructors. For further explanation and discussion of these drawings, see Peter Pennoyer's article on Delano as a student in the New-York Journal of American History, number 4.
  Drawings are arranged in two subseries by date, with undated drawings filed last. Unless otherwise noted, all drawings are graphite, ink, and wash on light paperboard, and uniform in size: 24-3/4 x 18-3/4 in. Titles given were inscribed by Delano [and descriptions in brackets for untitled drawings].
  - Subseries I: Exercises, Dated
    - Etablissement Financier, 1899 Jan. 4 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [screen on Legion of Honor?]
    - Un Theatre Municipal, 1899 Jan. 16 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Un Poste de Pompiers, 1899 Jan. 21 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [firehouse]
    - Une Ecurie d'Etat, 1899 Jan. 23 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [classical doorway]
    - Salle des pas Perdus, 1899 Feb. 10 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      [courthouse waiting room]
    - Une Fontaine Monumentale, 1899 Feb. 11 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Un Etablissement Thermal, 1899 Mar. 2 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      [casino facade?]
    - Entree d'une Cour d'Honneur, 1899 Mar. 8 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      [domed classical facade]
    - [Hotel Crillon, Place de la Concorde, measured drawing], 1899 Mar. 21 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Un Pavillon de Repos, 1899 Mar. 22 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Une Salle de Lecture, 1899 Mar. 31 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - [Untitled classical portico and facade, six columns], 1899 Apr. 7 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - [Untitled aquarium/marine laboratory facility], 1899 Sep. 6 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      watercolor, graphite, and ink on paper, 11-7/8 x 16 in.
    - Coupe parle cour de service..., 1899 Dec. 6 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      [slaughterhouse and market]; graphite and ink on gray paper, 23-7/8 x 17-3/4 in.
    - [Untitled design for public park], 1900 Feb. 7 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      brown ink and graphite on paper, 23-7/8 x 19 in.
    - [Untitled animal study/care facility], 1901 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      conte crayon and wash on Bristol board, 24-1/2 x 16-7/8 in.
  - Subseries II: Exercises, Undated
    - Une Bourse Maritime, [ca. 1899] (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Un Hotel de Ville, [ca. 1899] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      [city hall]
    - [Unidentified building, rez de chaussee (ground floor)], [ca. 1899] (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - [Untitled lecture hall], [ca. 1899] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      [perspective projection exercises]
    - [Untitled classical facade, perhaps archeological exercise], [ca. 1899] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      graphite on paper mounted on board, 19-3/4 x 18-1/4 in.
- Series III: Commissions
  Series III holds just three minor drawings for projects designed by Delano. Probably the most historically important inclusion is the only existing rendering of the first house ever designed by Delano, created for the mother of a friend in Ontario, Canada.
  Drawings are arranged chronologically.
  - Shaw, Mrs., Murray Bay, Ontario, Canada, house rendering, 1902 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    ink wash on paper mounted on pulpboard, 21-3/4 x 21 in.
  - Wood, Chalmers, Syosset, NY, house plan, [1927-1928] (Box 2, Folder 46)
    graphite and ink on paper mounted on board, 9-3/4 x 13-3/4 in.
  - White House, Washington, DC, main hall, 1949 Sep. 29 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    colored pencil on paper mounted on board, 10-1/2 x 18-1/2 in.
- Oversize Material from Series I: Photographs
  - Kahn, Otto H., estate (Oheka), Cold Spring Harbor, NY, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Staten Island Savings Bank, New York, NY, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - United States Government Building, Paris, France, Exteriors, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Unidentified airport [?] retail plaza and parking lot [?], undated (Box 2, Folder 50)